hello I'm your host David Barnard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in reany cat
state of subscription apps report each
episode in this series will explore one
crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Caroline walthal
director of product marketing and life
cycle marketing at Quizlet on the
podcast I talk with Caroline about the
importance of cancellation surveys
leveraging social proof in winback
campaigns and making it easier to cancel
can actually increase retention hey
Caroline thanks so much for joining me
on the podcast today thanks for having
me excited to dive into this topic so
we're going to talk about your top tips
for re-engaging turn users and
subscribers but before we get to those
tips I think it's really important to
understand why people unsubscribe before
you even think about and why people turn
out of your app so let's start with the
top reasons you see of why people turn
out of an app or turn out of a
subscription there's kind of three main
buckets of why people might turn from a
consumer subscription first of all they
may have hit a natural Breaking Point
with your product or your use case and
they don't need it anymore so like
that's kind of acceptable type of churn
in some ways and Quizlet the way that
happens often is students might graduate
from college and they don't have
constant tests anymore and so yeah we
may not be a amazing fit for them going
forward unless they're in certain
careers and career paths where they have
a lot of ongoing tests there's sort of
an acceptable turn that can happen and I
think sometimes people forget about that
like not all turn is literally bad some
of it you know is natural we were
hearing about this more and more in the
dating space as well of like hey you
know people turning from a dating app
that's actually good for them maybe not
good for the business but it's like you
kind of got to understand the business
you're in and understand those natural
turn Cycles as well there's also sort of
moments when customers didn't mean to
churn but something happened with their
payment method right their credit card
changed because of losing it or
something else happened you know and
they didn't update their information
there's a lot of things you can do to
address that level of sort of more
technical problem whether it's you know
really active communication proactively
before a renewal cycle comes up but also
Dunning you can work with specific
providers to help get to the root causes
and figure out how to make sure you're
able to apply new credit card numbers to
old credit cards things like that one of
the biggest categories and the thing
that I think we can zoom most into today
is maybe they didn't see the value right
we have to be honest like that's a huge
bucket as well and there's a lot of
things that go into that they may have
felt that the value that was offered
just wasn't meeting the cost of the
subscription or maybe it didn't perform
as expected maybe there were actual
issues with app or with the product
there could have been cheaper or easier
alternatives to access or maybe the
problem itself at the time felt like a
burning problem but when it came to
actually needing to have a solution for
it they realized it wasn't that burning
of a problem or that big of a problem
which sometimes happens for certain
segments and not others in your audience
how do you get at those things what's
the best way you found to understand why
people are churning and even with the
billing in the natural churn it's
sometimes helpful to understand that so
you're not sending them kind of the
wrong message or trying to win somebody
back when they've already graduated
college trying to figure out how to get
personalized information you know or
personalized reasons why people are
turning is great and cancellation survey
is an awesome thing to apply definitely
industry best practice so when people
decide to go through and cancel their
subscription with you you automatically
trigger some kind of several question
survey that just has some main
categories for the reasons why they're
done using the subscription at the time
and that can be just really helpful in
sizing and directing your turn
prevention efforts in the future and win
back efforts that follow and so we found
that helpful at Quizlet I would say as I
mentioned we have a good amount of
acceptable churn due to students aging
out but the challenge for Quizlet is
that onethird of those no longer need
users are just done with that more
pressing test or need that they had
maybe not actually done with college or
high school and so we have a challenge
to help people think about their
preparedness for tests and quizzes and
things like that on a more ongoing basis
so that's still a group we should be
targeting for example on a tactical
level do you only use predefined answer
shows questions or do you actually have
a text box and then what are are you
seeing anything especially crazy in that
text box I think we used to have a text
box we over time were able to really
kind of narrow it down to these buckets
that have been pretty consistent over
time it's a good idea probably to every
so often open that up and see if there's
more specific feedback that you can get
yet we do get a lot of good feedback
coming into to our user operations
channels separately to our help center
and the Agents that work on support at
Quizlet so we're able to kind of put
together the pieces from a few different
sources but yeah it is an option you can
leave a write in and I think especially
if you're just getting going probably a
good idea to do also a good idea to just
do some interviews with turning users
and understand more deeply what the
story is behind things and then create
your categories from there like if you
create those predetermined buckets out
of nowhere you might be missing kind of
significant cuts that you want to be
able to track over time so once folks
kind of have a a good handle on why
people are churning and we have three
top tips for us to re-engage those users
again to re-engage both the usage but
then also what we all want in this
industry is also to re-engage them as
subscribers as well so what are your top
three tips to re-engage those folks to
make sure you're delivering value is one
of the most important things you can do
here and that comes in a lot of
different forms right if you are
shipping new features and experiences
that you know people churned because you
didn't have them like you know you can
reach out to those people and let them
know hey we you asked we listened kind
of message but outside of that I would
say one of the best ways is just to
figure out how to deliver personalized
value through life cycle marketing based
on things that they've engaged with in
the past right so it might be using
segmentation or using dyamic variabl of
things that people have consumed before
so if your subscription is content based
using whatever categories you use to
break down content focus on providing
really useful recommendations for those
people bringing the freshness factor to
the table too of like you know we've got
new XYZ say you love dramas like on
Netflix or whatever it is right it's
like having that relevant sense that
like we know you we're not just sending
you random things or anything and
everything but we're leading with what
you've liked in the past and so I think
that can go a long way at Quizlet one of
the things we're doing is building out
kind of a social graph that's based on
the courses students are taking that
data kind of lets us send the most
relevant up-to-date hyper local content
that's coming from other students in
your course directly or from your school
I think that's the kind of thing that is
needed to capture people's attention
especially if they have decided to
cancel a subscription you know you need
to sort of win back and give them
reasons to believe that that you are
invested and that you have enough ways
to help them that maybe they haven't
tapped into before and it just helps
signal this idea of like maybe a little
bit of fomo right like there's other
students studying here there's other
customers like millions of people
accessing this or liking it like see why
you want to just keep things fresh at
the end of the day but you also want to
keep things personal so that's probably
my top one I think that works across
re-engaging users who just turn broadly
as well as subscribers who churn yeah
and on that level of like super kind of
hyper local content as you called it
yeah being able to say hey there's 20
other people studying this or even more
broadly like tens of thousands of
students are using us for their algebra
and we know you were taking algebra or
whatever and then kind of hitting them
with that that next test you're going to
score way better and you're going to
land higher on that bellur fuse Quizlet
because so many other people are the
social proof is big I think and
especially if you have enough usage to
actually like make those claims right
it's something to lean into and test
awesome what's tip number two yeah so
tip number two probably not
revolutionary but given consumer
subscriptions cost money and everybody's
got a finite amount to spend at the end
of the day a lot of people churn because
they're price sensitive right and so
cancellation discounts or other
personalized discounts to win back prior
Turners is definitely something to be
tried right you have to be careful in
how you approach this and you know
definitely recommend working with a data
scientist as you do so but essentially
you want to make these offers highly
targeted you can tiar them as well like
so you can give a bigger discount if
they were a subscriber for a longer
period of time consider a smaller
discount if they were you know maybe
only subscribing for a month or two and
so that's one way you can kind of
Balance cost Effectiveness a little bit
but you don't want it to be like a
blanket discount that you're offering
cuz at the end of the day a lot of times
that's going to really cut into your
overall bottom line in a way that isn't
really sustainable or if people learn
that triggering the cancellation flow
always means they're going to get a 50%
even if they say it's too expensive but
it wasn't really too expensive for them
right like you want to be careful with
that a little bit and you need to apply
some level of model like you know
whether it's bringing ml into things
right like you can do ml modeling or
just testing out some tearing structure
that you know helps you mitigate the
potential lost revenue from you know
over discounting offering discounts is
super helpful and again for a ton of
apps like it's probably just should be
the default but as you said like as you
get bigger like there's more things you
need to do and so I think tip number
three kind of speaks to that so what's
tip number three if you can't afford a
discount or you decide discounting is
complicated or maybe layering it on with
this discounting like these aren't
mutually exclusive tips here is to offer
more control over the terms of their
subscription so as I mentioned value
sometimes this is because there's value
there but it's more intermittent value
like maybe they only have that use case
every so often it's not a daily use case
or a weekly use case you know you can
try to think about how to offer shorter
subscription durations or give consumers
the ability to pause their subscription
when they are in sort of an offseason
for whatever that use case might be so
examples might be like Quizlet decided
to offer a monthly plan we tested into
offering that a few years ago because we
heard feedback that students wanted more
flexibility especially if they were
starting their subscription with us
partway through the school year they
didn't want to necessarily subscribe for
a whole year and so definitely you know
paying attention to the Natural cadences
for the use case can help and you can
just offer a new subscription duration
that you didn't have before you can also
give people as I mentioned the
opportunity to pause the subscription so
you could pause it and not pay for a few
months and then it makes you happier to
re-engage with it because you feel like
the subscription respected the fact that
as much as it might be a monthly Cadence
for some people or even for you
sometimes there's dependencies that you
can't always predict as to like how much
you actually need that in any given
month and so I think giving people
control builds trust there's a lot of
talk in in Tech and even more broadly in
society about subscription fatigue and
you know oh another subscription or
whatever and giving people control
really is and putting them at the center
and making them feel like they have
control is one of the better ways to
kind of build that trust and to make
them feel more comfortable with the
subscription and I mean I feel the exact
same way you know when there's a
subscription that I know is going to be
a pain to cancel or that I don't feel
those are the ones like I really avoid
like any other kind of tips around this
like helping people feel under control
you can offer bundled subscription links
as like a promo as well so say a lot of
folks use your product for a certain
duration like I would think about within
the edtech space if you're studying for
high stakes exams oftentimes you have
like a thre Monon window 3 to six Monon
window or something like that where
you're studying really intensely for
something like you know an entrance exam
like an MCAT or elsat or something like
that or you know other types of
professional exams that people study for
it's kind of in that realm and so you
could offer a specific bundle that's
like getting a deal for maybe not the
whole year but a half a year or a
quarter or something like that and you
know you don't necessarily have to
merchandise that as part of your normal
options all the time but if you see that
somebody is churning and that's a reason
why is that the length is not right or
something like that like you can offer
it then or maybe there's a Subs segment
that you know about like for like I
mentioned if we see you're studying for
specific exams maybe we can say hey
actually come back and use us for this
specific duration and get a little bit
of a deal on it so that's another way to
kind of bring in a little bit of
discounting into the duration piece and
then you also mentioned free trials and
offering a new free trial that's an
interesting one how do you think about
that and then how do you think about
kind of guarding against abuse of people
who will just kind of use that free
trial a second time just to get through
that one exam and then not ever pay
again so do you offer kind of refresh
free trial more judiciously yeah we do
it more judiciously for sure but we've
tested it at different points in time
and we've seen some success but you know
you'll see companies like LinkedIn I
feel like is a good example because I'll
get these like fairly frequently where
it's like they're trying to offer that
free Tri 30-day free trial again and you
know I've used it I think I've used
their like reup on trial before and I
think it did cause me to subscribe at
least one time and so it's like a
friendly on-ramp for something like
LinkedIn I think for students where
there is a bit more gaming maybe going
on too we do exercise caution on that a
little bit but it depends how long ago
that was right and if we see you come
back and we see you maybe are showing
certain signs of being an Engaged user
again like we you've really kind of come
back and you seem to be focused because
whatever classes you're taking that
semester are a great fit for Quizlet
yeah we maybe we should be refreshing
that trial for you because we all Al
usually have added a lot of value maybe
depending on how long it's been since
they last subscribed if it's pretty
recent I wouldn't really do that but if
it's been a year since they subscribed
often times it's a nice way to say hey
here's all the things we've added that's
great anything else you wanted to share
as we wrapped up yeah no I mean this has
been a great conversation I think the
only thing I'd say is at Quizlet we're
always hiring looking for great folks
who are passionate about helping
students and teachers and supporting the
learning process we've got an influencer
marketing specialist role that's open
right now if anybody you know has a
skill set that seems to match that and
we will be hiring for some other roles
on the marketing team coming up likely
life cycle marketing analyst role so
keep an eye out on the quizlet.com
careers page and yeah we'd love to have
great smart folks join us a lot of great
smart folks in this audience so uh
hopefully that'll drum up a few
interesting candidates quizly just it's
another one of those I feel like there's
several like really cool big subscript
companies I actually spoken to several
of them in this series with the SATA
subscription apps podcast that just
aren't on people's radar it's like
everybody talks about dualingo or stra
or kind of those big ones but then
there's a lot of really cool companies
like Quizlet and onx and others in the
space that just don't get talked about
as much so if you're in the industry and
you're looking for a new role quiz's a
fantastic company been around a long
time doing a lot of really cool stuff so
uh great place to join Caroline thank
you so much for joining me today it's
been so fun and thanks for sharing all
your great tips thanks David it's been
really great appreciate
it thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community
[Music]